S2 Module 1: What is Zero Knowledge (like, actually)? with David Wong
Nico: Welcome to Season 2 of
the ZK Whiteboard Sessions.
I'm Nico, I'll be today's host.
And with me I have David from zkSecurity.
David: Hey guys.
Nico: If you have not yet, I
encourage you to check out Season 1,
because we are going to be building
upon what was learnt in those modules.
There's also a study club in the ZK Hack Discord
where we go over the sessions week after week.
Actually, it's by doing those
sessions that we realized
a few things were missing or
a few things needed updates.
So we're back with a new set of modules
sponsored by a grant from the Ethereum
Foundation ZK Grants program.
And today's module is going
to be about "What is ZK"?
And I mean, "What is zero knowledge?"
The actual cryptographic property.
And this is something that's
really important because,
in all the episodes we have,
we didn't really cover this.
So, David, today we're going to go over
the theory, some of the practice as well,
and see if our good friend,
PLONK, is zero knowledge.
David: Yeah. Cool.
Yeah. So everybody always talks about ZKP,
Zero Knowledge Proofs and these kind of things.
And the ZK is always kind of like mysterious
and it's almost like we
don't really care about it.
So I guess we're going to dig
more into what exactly it is.
The first thing we can talk about is sort
of a high level, what is the API of ZK?
Nico: Sure.
So if you think of a prover and a verifier,
all of these things and you really abstract it,
what they're really doing is that they're
proving a program or a statement or whatever.
In our days and age, we think about programs
because we're like general-purpose ZKP.
And so here we have like some
-- let's say, some function.
And this function takes some arguments.
Maybe I'll write that bigger ARG2,
arg1. Maybe put us some outputs.
And this is purely computational.
Like you're running that on your computer
and maybe you want to prove to me that
running this function with these
arguments gives this output. Right?
And so usually when we talk about ZK, ZK comes
in place when you want to mask something.
Like you want to prove to me
that you're computing this thing,
but you don't really want
to show me these arguments.
So a typical example is like
this is a Sudoku Solver.
This is like a grid of a Sudoku
that's missing some squares.
And this is the actual
solution, and this is like "true,
this is a good solution" and you're masking that.
Nico: Makes sense.
David: Hopefully that makes sense.
This is really --
I always tell people, if you want to
think about ZK, don't think about ZK,
think about pure computation and then
think about what you want to mask.
And you don't need to understand how ZK works,
you can just think of it from a high level.
It seems like a lot of people sometimes care
more about the succinctness of modern schemes.
So we don't really talk about
ZK so much in modern schemes.
People tend to talk about zk-SNARKs or SNARKs.
Maybe I'll write it down.
And the succinctness comes from that S.
I don't know how to write "succinctness".
I always mess it up, but I will try.
And people can correct me at home if they want.
And basically this says, okay, you're
going to prove to me this computation,
but when I'm going to verify your proof, which
is kind of a signature over that computation,
it's going to take me less time to
verify it than it would have taken me to,
like if you send me the arguments
to run the function myself.
Nico: I see.
David: Right? So there's kind of a --
Like ZKPs have really two interesting things.
You can mask some of the --
You can prove to me a computation, you
can mask some of the inputs or outputs.
Again, here you can mask that or you can
mask that, or you can mask whatever you want.
Nico: Sure.
Although it's not very useful
if you mask everything.
But also you can -- there's a succinctness aspect
where it's very cheap for me to verify a proof.
Nico: So succinctness and zero
knowledge are two separate properties
and you can have one without the other, or --
David: Exactly, exactly.
Some schemes are not succinct,
some schemes are not ZK.
And as we'll see, actually
most schemes are not ZK,
and ZK is sort of like, you can
add it at the end if you want,
either for free or like
you have to think about it.
And maybe we should mention that a
lot of schemes don't even use the ZK
like modern zk-Rollups or so-called zk-Rollups.
Nico: Are not ZK?
David: Are not really ZK because
they don't actually mask anything.
They mostly care about compressing all that
computation in a way that's easy to verify.
It's like -- yeah.
Nico: So should we define ZK?
Like what do we mean? What is --
David: Okay. So --
Nico: -- it's property?
David: At a high level this is that.
But if we look at deeper --
there's a deeper meaning behind it.
And as cryptographers, we have to
think about the deeper meaning.
So the way we can think about it is that--
You know, imagine I'm the
prover and you're the verifier.
I want to prove something to you, but there's
-- I really want to hide that stuff from you.
Like we can think of these schemes
where usually that's what we do, right?
We're like communicating.
I'm sending you a message, you're sending
me a message, I'm sending you a message.
We go back and forth.
Actually, a lot of very basic
schemes are just three messages,
which are called "Sigma protocol",
because of the shape of the Sigma.
And here I really want to prove something to you,
but I don't want to, like I said, leak this thing.
And so the idea is that -- or a
way that we try to theorize that,
which is kind of hard to understand
actually, is that if I was talking to --
Maybe I can --
So I'm the prover, right?
Nico: Sure.
David: And I don't know if we're going to talk
about soundness at some point, but this is --
Nico: Sure. I think --
David: Maybe I should mention it also.
But there's kind of competing
properties of proof systems.
As the verifier, you want to
make sure I'm not lying to you,
but as the prover, I want to make sure you're
not getting information from me, right?
Nico: Makes sense.
David: And so as the prover
-- or, sorry, as the verifier,
you want to see if you can distinguish
between this wall where you're talking to me,
and you're trying to obtain information from me,
or you're talking to what we call a 'simulator'.
So this is how we get into the theory of it.
Nico: Okay.
David: And if you can talk to a simulator that
has no idea about the Sudoku solution or whatever,
and they give you the same result as if
you were talking to me, a real prover,
then -- like you can't really tell if
you're talking to me or to a simulator
that doesn't even know about the actual --
we should call it witness at this point,
then the scheme is zero knowledge.
So that's my introduction to it.
Maybe it doesn't make sense, but I wanted
to introduce the idea of simulator.
Nico: So the intuition behind this is even
though the simulator doesn't know the witness,
we can have this interaction?
David: Right.
And I'll write "witness" here
because we just used the word.
So witness is the stuff that we're trying to mask.
So maybe I'll write the API of a simulator.
But imagine that this argument is
actually not ZK, like it's public,
we say that usually this is the statements.
So a statement usually is what's known in public
and the witness is what you're trying to mask.
And so the simulator, let's say S
usually just take the statements --
usually x is the statement, w is
the witness, doesn't really matter,
usually just take the statements.
Whereas a prover, on the other hand
usually takes a statement and a witness.
So "Sudoku grid" and "Sudoku solution".
And so you're thinking if I
can, sort of as a verifier,
just talk to a simulator that doesn't
know anything about the witness,
and it looks the same as with the prover,
then when I interact with a prover,
I don't really learn anything either.
Nico: That makes sense.
Should we maybe see a concrete
example of a simulator?
David: A good example to see these kind
of things is to look at the Schnorr --
Is this how you write "Schnorr"?
Nico: Correct. Yeah.
David: Schnorr identity protocol.
And Schnorr identity protocol is something pretty
simple that is at the base of Schnorr signatures.
And actually ECDSA signatures sort of
follow the same -- like a similar pattern.
And this is a proof, a zero knowledge
proof of a discrete logarithm.
Nico: Okay.
So here in this setting,
the prover knows the discrete logarithm
of a value Y. So we'll call that x.
And they want to prove to the verifier, -- so
I'm the prover, you're the verifier, right?
Nico: Cool.
David: They want to prove that
they know the x here. Right?
So the way it works -- this is a
three-step protocol, the Sigma protocol.
The way it works is that you usually
send -- you commit to a value.
Nico: Small r maybe?
David: I'll call it r. Yeah.
You commit to a value that you
generated hopefully randomly,
and then you receive a challenge from
the verifier that hopefully is random,
and we'll talk more about that.
And then you send something which is, let's
see if I can remember it, r + c . x.
So that's the value you can
compute as the prover because
you know x times the challenge
plus the value you committed.
And this protocol is sound and complete,
as we say in zero knowledge proof,
meaning that it works.
If I know the value x, I can
prove it to you it's complete,
and it's sound, I cannot lie to
you if I don't know the value x.
Nico: Are we missing a verification step here?
David: Yeah. What does the verifier do at the end?
Let's see also if I can remember that.
So z obviously is something that you
need to raise. So they will raise z.
And they will check if it's equal to
-- there's many ways to do that check,
but that's a way you can do it.
yᶜ. Because yᶜ --
Nico: Plus r. No?
David: We can -- times R, right?
Let's open it.
So yᶜ is gˣᶜ . gʳ
And so -- yeah, which is z; is it?
All right, we got it right on the first try.
Okay. So that scheme is -- you know, it's
nice, it works, it's using Schnorr signatures.
Let's see why it's ZK or
let's see why it's not ZK.
Nico: Sounds good.
David: Okay. Let's wipe that.
So we're going to take the idea of a simulator,
and here what the simulator wants to
do, or you as like you're the verifier,
you're going to call that simulator
and see if you can make it work.
And basically the way it works here
is that you want to form a transcript
that looks like Message₁, Message₂, Message₃,
which are the first point, the challenge
and that z. And you want it to verify --
Nico: This equation?
David: Exactly.
Even though the simulator, who produces
that doesn't know the x. Right?
So the way they do it is
that basically they go out of order.
They know that the verifier is
going to sample some random value.
So they choose a random c in advance,
and then they choose a random
z actually, they don't care.
They're so powerful. They don't care.
And then they're going to say -- they're going
to know that they did things out of order.
They're going to say that m1 or whatever R is --
Okay. Let's think about it. So you
want that equation to work, right?
Nico: Yeah.
David: And --
Nico: So we know this and we
know this, so can we set this.
David: Right. So you want r -- oh, sorry. It's
big R, right? You want big R to be equal to -
We can look at that equation here, to be equal
to gᶻ divided by yᶜ or multiplied by y⁻ᶜ.
And you know this value. You
know everything here, basically,
and so you can compute that
and the equation will check.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: Does that make sense? Yeah.
And so that's it.
That's the transcript that
the simulator can produce,
and they didn't know the witness.
They just formed this R out of nowhere.
You can verify these transcripts
and it doesn't really tell you
anything about any witness, and --
Nico: I see.
David: And basically that's the idea.
Nico: And so this is why the Schnorr
identity protocol is zero knowledge,
because we are able to produce this?
David: So it's not zero knowledge per
se, because here we made an assumption.
We actually made the assumption that the
challenge here is sampled uniformly --
from a uniform distribution.
And so that's not always true.
Nico: Right.
David: Verifiers might get nasty
and try to learn stuff from you
and might send you specific values to
try and leak information from your data.
And so we made an assumption in this
case which we called Honest -- one n,
Honest-Verifier ZK.
And so usually we write HVZK.
And so it's important to note
because when you want to write
proofs which are simulator-based,
you want to try and understand
what can the simulator do.
If you always start with an
honest verifier assumption,
in which case the verifier can choose
these challenges by themselves,
or just say that they received
all the challenges in advance
and they know exactly what
the challenges look like.
These are two similar models.
But if you're -- usually we don't --
I mean, there's two camps.
One camp doesn't really like the HVZK, the
Honest Verifier ZK, because they can --
maybe there's some attacks where they
can leak things from your witness.
And maybe we can either both ways now.
We can either talk about that or we can talk about
why actually Honest Verifier
ZK is okay these days.
Nico: So I do have one question
before we jump into those topics.
It's what prevents a malicious
prover from doing exactly this,
and proving something without
knowledge of a witness?
David: So this doesn't break the soundness,
very good question,
because here we went out of order.
Nico: Right.
David: Like we knew the challenge in advance,
so we created that R after knowing the challenge.
Whereas these schemes are
really a commit and reveal --
well, there's no reveal actually, but
they're commits and then receive a challenge.
And in this case it's important
that you're following that order.
Nico: Okay.
David: Yeah. So honest verifier, do
we want that, do we not want that?
If we're doing an interactive
protocol, it really matters.
And so in that sense we don't want the verifier to
send us malicious challenges that can leak stuff.
And so it turns out that --
for example, in this example
the Schnorr ID protocol,
this is not dishonest verifier ZK
because there are some issues here
and we don't actually know
how to write a simulator
that will show you something that
you can verify and that works.
And the reason is that if we assume
that this might not be uniformly random,
then the simulator basically has to
guess what the challenge will be.
So they are at this step, they have to
produce some R while guessing the c.
They come here and then they call the verifier.
So we say that the simulator here
has oracle access to the verifier.
And so they will see that the challenge
is not actually what they thought about
because probably the sample space is pretty large.
And so they go back and they retry.
And they can do that many times, but the idea is
that they're bounded, their runtime is bounded,
and so they most likely will never find a
challenge that never guess the actual challenge.
Nico: I see.
David: If they could guess the actual challenge,
then it probably would mean
that this scheme is not secure.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: And so -- well, actually I'm going
to backtrack on that, but you'll see why.
So a way to make this actually "dishonest
verifier ZK" or just plain ZK as we say,
is to have the challenge c
sample from a very small domain.
So actually if you --
Maybe I'll use a different color.
No. All right. Just keep on that.
If you sample c from 0 or 1 like a bit,
then we can prove that this is plain ZK
because now the simulator
can, with good estimates --
Nico: Try to guess --
David: Guess if it's going to be 0 or 1,
if it's with expectation of two tries.
So maybe the first time
they're not going to get it,
but the second time they're expected to get it.
And that's fine because the simulator can do that.
They are a polynomial bounded algorithm.
Nico: Does this come at some kind of
cost? Maybe a penalty on soundness?
David: Yeah.
So it kind of sucks, right?
Because the real prover in that case has basically
1 out of 2 chance to guess the
challenge correctly as well.
And so it sucks because they might --
half of the time, even if they don't know
the witness, they'll correctly prove.
So usually in these schemes what you want
to do is repeat it many, many, many times.
Because here the soundness is
like, well, I guess 1 over 2.
But if you repeat it many,
many times, you decrease the --
the prover will have to guess the correct c like
100 times in a row without
mistakes, and that's harder.
Or I don't know how many times.
Nico: So you said Schnorr
signatures are based on this idea.
I'm guessing we're not doing
this with our Schnorr signatures.
David: Right. Let's --
We're not repeating the protocol many times.
Yeah.
That would suck.
So in Schnorr signatures, we
have a non-interactive protocol,
which I guess I'm going to
sort of not mention too much.
But it's basically I can create a proof there
is no interaction. You can just verify it.
And to do that we use a transformation called
Fiat–Shamir, because there were two guys,
one was called Fiat, one was called Shamir, if I
remember correctly, but I don't think I was born,
and they invented this thing where basically,
if you know these are public coin messages,
which means that they're random and public.
Nico: From a big distribution, right?
David: From a big distribution.
Nico: Cool.
David: But I would -- yeah.
If you know -- so we call them "public coin
messages", but it doesn't really matter.
But it's just the term that we
use. It's public randomness.
Then you can replace these
things by a hash function.
Basically, that's the idea.
But of course, in theory we
call them "random oracles".
And this whiteboard is starting to get crowded --
Nico: Crowded, yeah.
David: But it's fine.
And so when we start using hash functions --
Right now we're still in the ideal model.
So we're still using ideal constructions.
But when we're going to instantiate
these, usually we use hash functions.
And so once we switch to these things,
we say that we're in the
random oracle model or ROM.
This is kind of the lingo.
It doesn't matter too much, but it's good to know.
Nico: Yeah.
David: And so what we do here is that we replace
any interaction from the verifier by hashes.
In these Sigma protocols, it's pretty easy.
You just hash that first part.
So a transcript would look like --
like you would remove the challenge.
And when you would verify these
transcripts, you would basically use --
Here, instead of this c, you
would use a hash of R, right?
Nico: And maybe y, I'm guessing.
David: And maybe the statement.
And so that's where it gets tricky.
So like people never know
like what are you supposed
to include in the Fiat–Shamir transformation.
And usually you want to include --
The answer is you want to include
as many things as possible.
And I believe there were actually some problem
when people instantiated signatures where they
didn't include the public
key, which is the y here.
Famously EdDSA included the
public key, so they were less --
Some contrived attacks were less annoying.
But yeah.
And so it may be worth mentioning,
but in these days and age,
we have more modern SNARKs.
And they're sort of like Sigma
protocols, but they're much longer,
they have more challenges.
And so here the Fiat–Shamir
transformation is a bit trickier.
You have to constantly hash --
You have to continuously hash the transcript
up to that point to create these challenges.
And there's a lot of bugs in these kind of things.
Nico: So in this case, we've replaced our verifier
by the random oracle or the hash function.
Does that mean it now behaves
honestly and this is enough?
David: Yeah. So the idea here is that
in this model you can either say
the Fiat–Shamir stuff is a compiler,
and if we're in the honest
verifier model, then it's fine.
Like we're not in ZK.
Nico: Right.
David: It's secure. Or you
can say that you're in --
You can analyze this in a different way
where you can say that you're in the EP ROM.
Let's write it here. EP ROM.
Nico: What does E and P stand for?
David: So E is for Explicit Programmable or
Explicitly Programmable, or you know, English --
Two M, I believe.
Explicitly programmable.
And that means that basically,
once you reach the challenge
where you're supposed to
do a hash of, let's say, R,
let's include the statements, because YOLO.
And once you do that, once you have
your call to that random oracle,
you can basically --
the simulator will basically choose -- will
program the random oracle and choose the answer.
Nico: Right.
David: And so they basically have a superpower.
And without that superpower, they wouldn't
be able to create a valid transcript.
Nico: Right.
Right. Because we needed to know
this value before knowing R?
David: Right.
Nico: Interesting.
David: So far I haven't really talked about
the CRS stuff and there's more superpowers,
but maybe before we get there, maybe let's talk
about the different flavors of zero knowledge.
Nico: Sounds good.
David: And then we can talk
about our famous SNARKs
and how simulators can do things in that world,
rather than Sigma protocols,
which are fairly simple.
Nico: Sounds good.
David: So what are the three flavors of ZK?
We talk about ZK as perfect ZK. That's a
flavor most people like. This is chocolate.
And the second flavor of ZK
is -- yeah, statistical ZK.
And the third flavor of ZK is computational ZK.
Nico: And in all these cases, we get honest
verifier and malicious verifier variants?
David: Yeah. So you can combine all of that.
In every case, there's --
So you can do all the combinations of ice cream.
Nico: Choose my toppings.
David: Yeah.
And this is probably like
vanilla or something like that.
We don't like this one too much.
I mean, it depends on people.
But that's fine. It doesn't mean it's bad.
Nico: So what's the differences
between the -- our three flavors?
David: So to understand the difference, we
sort of have to look into probabilities.
Nico: Okay.
David: And so I've been talking about simulators
and how a verifier can interact with a simulator
and how the simulator can have Oracle
access to the verifier and stuff like that.
Maybe it's a bit confusing.
So let's put it in writing.
As usual in cryptography, we play games
and then we check the
probabilities of these games.
So I can never remember this one. So
let's see if I get it on the first try.
But here we're playing a game where
the verifier is sort of the adversary.
Like they want to check if they
really can talk to the simulator
and talk to the prover and
see if there's a difference.
So we get an instance and a witness, or vice
versa -- sorry, a witness and an instance.
We get them from the adversary.
And then we're going to
get a random bit at random.
And then we're going to say,
this proof is created by a prover on the
witness and statements if b equals 0,
or by the simulator if b equals 1.
So basically we're playing this game,
but we don't know if we're talking to the
prover or we're talking to the simulator.
Nico: Right.
David: And then the adversary --
And I'm kind of simplifying here, the adversary
usually take more inputs, but who cares? YOLO.
And now the adversary takes the proof and the
statements and responds with, let's say, b prime.
And basically the adversary
is trying to guess, right?
If they're talking to the prover or the simulator,
they're trying to distinguish, actually.
So you might see a d here in some definition.
Nico: Right.
David: And here we want to check the probability
that they actually made a good guess.
Does that make sense?
Nico: Yeah.
David: Does that make sense?
I might be forgetting some
details, but that's the idea.
So let's look at it again.
Adversary chooses the instance and witness,
and either the prover or the simulator creates a
proof and then they have to try and figure out --
Nico: Figure out which one. Okay. So
this probability should be, I guess --
David: What's the best case?
Nico: The best case for us?
Well, One half, right?
We're trying to guess a bit.
David: Right.
Nico: So it's a 50-50 chance.
David: Exactly.
So if this probability is one half --
Nico: We're very happy.
David: Or is exactly one half,
actually, we're in the perfect world.
Nico: Right.
David: All right.
This is, we're happy.
If it's around one half, up
to some negligible value,
I'll just write it like that, I guess,
but usually there's better ways to
write it, but it doesn't really matter.
If it's almost close to one half,
we say that it's statistical.
And now if it's almost close to one
half, but the adversary is bounded,
because so far we basically assume that
the adversary was unbounded up to --
Nico: Unlimited power.
David: Unlimited power.
So that's also interesting.
But if now we're limiting
the power of the adversary,
which is actually not too bad of
an assumption in the real world,
because computers are bounded and so on, then
we say that we're in the computational ZK.
Nico: Okay. I mean, things like discrete
log are computational, right? So.
David: Yeah. So --
Nico: We might as well keep going.
David: Yeah, exactly.
So if you look at how different proofs
are created or different attacks,
you can see that sometimes the
adversary will be able to compute this.
And so these proofs are usual in these models.
Nico: Wow, okay.
So, David, I wanted to ask,
how does this now apply to,
I guess protocols that we're more
familiar with in this series?
Something like PLONK, let's say?
David: So, I guess --
Yeah. Let me make some room on the --
Nico: On the side?
David: The whiteboard.
We don't care about Schnorr
because that's a Sigma,
and we're talking about PLONK or modern SNARKs.
Nico: Yeah.
David: So there's a few different ways to do ZK
or to try to create these --
send proofs with simulators.
But of course, things are more
complex, we have a lot of interaction,
we have a lot of messages, like
in the transcripts at the end.
So it's kind of hard to explain
everything here on the whiteboard session,
but the thing we can do is
simplify what PLONK looks like
or what these protocols looks like.
And if you look essentially at a proof in PLONK,
what it looks like is an array of commitments,
like I don't know, c₁, c₂, c₃, etc,
and an array of evaluations, e₁, e₂, e₃, etc.
Is there more to these schemes?
I don't think so.
But I believe it's commitments, polynomial
commitments and evaluation at some points.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: And so when we look at
that, the idea is that it's --
or maybe an insight is that it's easier to
make this ZK if these things look random.
The more random these things
look like, the more ZK it is.
If you imagine that all of these things are
purely, uniformly random, then it's purely ZK.
Nico: Yeah. Well, the simulator
can just put out random stuff.
David: Exactly.
As the simulator, you just
pick random stuff and --
Nico: Cool.
David: Exactly. But if you do that,
then the scheme is not very sound,
because then if everything's
random, how do you even --
Nico: Because we still need to
pass the verification step, right?
David: Right, right.
Nico: Okay.
David: But if you pass the verification
step just by choosing random values,
then the prover can do the
same, and then what's the point?
Nico: Fair
David: Okay. So let's look at the commitments first,
and then we'll look at the evaluations.
So you have different types of commitments.
We have KZG, Pedersen commitments,
you can use hashes and so on.
And so here, to make commitments look random,
we want to look at the hiding
property of commitments.
Nico: Okay.
David: So maybe let me write
that -- hiding commitments.
And what does it mean that a commitment is hiding?
By the way, commitments have to be
binding or they have different properties,
but I'm not going to say anything about that.
I'm only going to talk about hiding.
Hiding basically means that it looks more
random and it hides what's committed.
Remember earlier we were talking about
commitments with the Schnorr protocol
by just hiding stuff in the exponents.
But here, we're going to talk about
maybe simpler commitments to start with.
We can talk about hashes.
Nico: Okay.
David: Right?
Nico: Yeah. Let's do that.
David: So imagine I want to create
a commitment from hashing a value,
this is not super secure as is.
Nico: Okay.
David: Actually, let me ask you why.
Do you see why this is not the best commitment?
Nico: In terms of hiding?
David: In terms of hiding, yeah.
Nico: Well, I guess every time I commit to
v, I'll always have the same commitment.
David: True.
Nico: I guess, somewhat deterministic, right?
David: Yeah. It's deterministic.
Yeah. If you have two commitments and
you already know the commitment value,
you can distinguish them.
Nico: Yes. Makes sense.
David: Any other reason that you can think of?
Nico: I guess --
David: That's a good one.
Nico: If I know candidate values, maybe v1, v2,
I can hash v1 and v2 to see which one you used.
David: Right.
So you can try values by yourself,
and if this is part of the values you can
try, you can also see that it's not a --
you can discover the value behind it.
So basically you're right.
With these examples, we can
clearly see that it's not hiding.
And you can think of other things,
like if v is pretty small, you can
try all the values from zero --
Nico: Brute force it?
David: From zero to one and stuff like that.
So how do we fix that?
Basically what we can do is that we
can append some randomness. And I --
Nico: Is this r the same as that r?
I'm guessing, no, right?
David: Yeah.
Nico: Yeah. Yeah. Let's remove this now.
David: Let's remove that.
Nico: Cool.
David: So by appending some randomness to
the hash, then you make it impossible to --
I guess, to compute the hash and see if it checks,
because you don't know what that randomness is.
And if that randomness is large enough, then --
Nico: I can't brute force it, right?
David: You cannot brute force it.
Exactly.
There's other --
Nico: So now, if I commit to v multiple times,
I'll have different randomness and the
commitment will be different every time, right?
David: Exactly, also.
So every time you commit, you sample r randomly
and so you get random different commitments.
And so here, if you imagine that
you are using a hash function,
then this is one way of really hiding it.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: And this will --
We can also talk about the distribution,
but since r is randomly distributed,
then the commitment is also uniformly
distributed across the space.
Nico: Makes sense. And now our
simulator is going to be happy.
David: Exactly.
Very easy to simulate.
You just pick random values and that's fine.
Nico: So you showed us also this commitment
from the Schnorr protocol with g to some power.
How would we randomize it in that case?
David: Yeah. g to the power x.
Actually, maybe it's something that I didn't
mention previously, but in our simulator,
we really want things to look like the
same distribution as a real prover.
So here, if the real prover is doing things that
are really uniformly distributed on the domain,
then it's easier to create a simulator
because you can just pick things that are
uniformly distributed on the same domain.
And so people won't be able to distinguish them.
But if this is distributed over like some values
and the simulator can pick
different values, different sets,
then these sets are different and then it's easier
for the distinguisher to differentiate them.
So that's something that's --
when you create a simulator, that's something
you have to keep in mind all the time.
You have to do something that's exactly the
same set as a real prover in perfect ZK,
or almost the same set in
statistical ZK or computational ZK.
And so the insight here is that it's
easier to do that if it's purely random,
if it looks purely random.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: Which is in our case with
the hash, but not here, right?
Nico: Yes.
David: So Pedersen commitments are already here.
I never know how to write it, but
I think this is how you write it.
Nico: That's correct.
David: Pedersen commitments
are basically very simple.
You just multiply this with another base,
which you don't know the discrete
log of, raised to the power r.
This is your randomness.
Nico: Again. Okay.
David: And so here, basically, this
will give you any points in your group,
and so we're back to like a very good hiding.
Nico: Something that looks random. Okay.
David: In the case of KZG, you have
something very similar to that,
except that people don't really
use it because of the costs.
And so we don't have this perfect hiding and
so we have to do some other randomization.
Nico: So we'll get probably
something computationally hiding?
David: No.
Nico: No. Okay.
David: Because we'll actually
randomize things in a good way.
Nico: Okay. That's great.
David: So we're still in the perfect hiding.
Nico: Okay. So we've now --
David: [?]
Nico: We now have a method to
hide our PLONK commitments.
How do we deal with the evaluations?
David: Okay. So --
So these commitments are not commitments of values
where we're talking about polynomials.
And so you have to think of polynomials are
like a polynomial f of a degree d, right?
This is what we're talking about.
Nico: Yeah.
David: And so if you start giving --
If I start giving you evaluations
of that polynomial of degree d,
I'm starting to leak information
about that polynomial.
Actually, let me ask you a question.
How many evaluations do you need to
recover my polynomial f of a degree d?
Nico: That would be d + 1.
David: d + 1, right?
By definition, if you have d + 1 evaluations,
you know exactly the
description of the polynomial.
Nico: Yeah.
David: That's good enough.
So obviously we don't want to have d +
1 evaluation for the same polynomial,
otherwise we're screwed.
But even one evaluation is bad
enough, because this might --
this evaluation is really tied to
the polynomial and to the witness.
And so this might give some
advantage to our adversary.
They might be able to distinguish --
Nico: Well, now they only need to find
d values because they already got 1,
if they're trying to collect d + 1.
David: Well, we --
Nico: I'm guessing we've given 1 to them.
David: Yeah. But they won't be able to get
d + 1, but maybe one is enough to distinguish.
Nico: I see.
David: Because they just have to distinguish,
right? They don't have to recover f.
Nico: We're in this game.
David: They just have to play that game, right?
So the way we do things is that
we randomize these polynomials.
Nico: What does that mean?
David: So what does that mean?
We basically want --
because if we randomize the polynomial, then
we don't have the same polynomial, right?
And if we add randomness in the polynomial,
and so it kind of messes the protocol,
and then the verifier doesn't have
something they can actually check.
So this randomization has to be controlled.
It has to preserve the rules of the games and
the identities that we want to do in PLONK.
And so it's, I don't know,
a controlled randomization.
Nico: Okay.
David: I don't know how much I need to recap here,
but in PLONK you have these vanishing polynomials,
and we do stuff on a domain, the circuit
domain, where we chose a bunch of points.
Nico: So actually, maybe we can write this down.
We have our roots of unity. I think
those were covered in previous sessions.
David: Okay.
So let's say we have a domain H,
which is the domain generated by, let's
say, g, our generator, or -- yeah, or the --
Nico: I think they've been using
Omega in the previous sessions.
David: Omega? All right. Let's use that.
Nico: If that'll be helpful.
David: And we also --
So you must have seen a vanishing polynomial,
which you can write in a succinct way.
Maybe I'll write the size of H here, minus one.
And all the roots of unity, or the Omega
roots of unity will basically cancel
when raised to the power the size of
their domain, the order of their group.
And so we have a nice succinct
description of our polynomial,
our vanishing polynomial.
Nico: Okay.
David: If that doesn't make sense, I guess
people can just go back to previous videos.
Nico: Cool.
David: So the way our f works.
So imagine that there's some polynomial in
our PLONK or STARK, or whatever, which is f.
And we want to create some
f prime which is randomized.
What we're going to do is that f
prime is going to be equal to f --
Nico: As before.
David: As before, plus our vanishing polynomial
times, let's call it g, times g of x.
Nico: Do you want maybe a different
letter to avoid conflict here?
David: Oh. Damn it. m.
Nico: Yeah, m --
David: Let's do m of x. All right.
So when we're looking at that,
we still have that f prime of x is
equal to f of x when we're in our domain.
Nico: So when we're evaluating at these Omegas.
David: At these Omega or powers of Omegas, right?
Nico: I see. Because --
David: Because this thing here will be zero.
Nico: Right?
David: Right? Whenever we have x is equal
to a power of Omega, that right side --
Nico: Disappears.
David: Disappears.
Nico: Cool.
David: But when we're not, and
usually when we have evaluations here,
we evaluate these polynomials at
points that are outside of our domain.
Nico: Right.
David: Not necessarily, but with high
probability, high probability enough,
because our domain is pretty small.
Then this thing will activate and
will randomize our evaluations.
Nico: So what is m in this case?
David: So m, in this case, is a random polynomial,
you know m(x) = r₀ + r₁X + r₂X²,
and so on.
And the number of random values here, or
the degree of that random polynomial m,
is dictated by the number of evaluations.
So, the more evaluations, the
more randomness you want to have.
Nico: I see.
David: And there's a --
I guess there is different
ways to prove that this works.
Maybe a way to prove that this works is
that if you evaluate this in, let's say,
if you evaluate f prime in two
points, you can see that you can --
so, we have f prime of I don't know,
alpha₁ and f prime of alpha₂.
If you evaluate that at two
points, then you can see that --
If you evaluate that at two points, then
you can see that you can basically --
and you give them whatever values you
want, you can see that you can recover --
you have a system of equations, basically.
If you have enough random
values, so let's say two.
You have two unknowns in a system of
equations of linearly independent equations --
Of two linearly independent equations.
And so, you can solve it.
Nico: Right.
David: I don't know if that made sense,
but that's one way you can try
to think about it, basically.
I'll rephrase that in a different way,
but you can obtain any evaluations you
want for two points if you have two --
if you have a degree 1 polynomial,
if you have two randomness coefficients.
And so if you have more evaluations,
you want more randomness coefficients.
Nico: So I guess the last question I had is, what
is the total degree of this f prime polynomial?
David: All right.
So because we're adding stuff here, unfortunately,
we're raising the degree of this thing.
And so it's going to be basically f most likely
is already the degree of the vanishing polynomial.
Just because of PLONK or
whatever we're doing for -- for reasons.
Nico: Sure.
David: But m here is the
number of evaluation minus one.
Nico: Minus one.
David: Right.
Because if you do two evaluations,
you have a degree 1 polynomial.
And so you're going to --
Basically, you're multiplying
that, and so if this is degree n,
then you get n + 2, if
you have two evaluations.
And so you're increasing the -- you have a,
d + 2 maybe, or d + 3, or something like that.
So you're adding some degrees,
which can be annoying.
Nico: Right.
Because it's a cost to the prover, the verifier.
David: Yeah. Yeah, basically.
Nico: Cool. Shall we look at KZG?
David: Oh, yeah.
So we talked about hash, I guess, in Pedersen,
let's briefly mention KZG.
So KZG has a different way to do commitments.
I guess, you've talked about
that in previous sessions.
Nico: Yeah. Session 1, absolutely.
David: So commitments of a function is basically
the commitment of that
function at some secret points.
Should I -- maybe a Tau, I guess.
And so you're not really --
You're revealing something, especially
against an adversary that's unbounded.
Nico: Right. That makes sense.
David: When you're trying to do these
proofs, you're revealing the discrete log.
So the adversary can just see
that if they're unbounded.
Nico: So we revealed one of the evaluations of f.
David: Right. So what's the
natural way of hiding that?
Nico: Like we just did earlier.
David: Exactly.
Nico: Adding more.
David: You just add more randomness
in this masking polynomial.
So nothing magical.
Yeah. You see that as an evaluation.
Nico: Cool.
David: So maybe it's worth mentioning,
but PLONK is instantiated with
KZG or different commitments.
Mina uses Pedersen commitments.
And so depending on the commitment you're using,
you have different hiding polynomials.
But you have different degrees.
Nico: That makes sense. I had
another question, which is,
when we're working with KZG,
we have this trusted setup.
Where does the trusted setup happen
in this game, and does it matter?
David: Because we're still --
As I said, we still want to create these
proofs with a simulator to prove ZK,
we still care about perfect or statistical
or computational ZK and all these things.
So this is basically the same.
Like we're still in that model,
except that we have one more step where
we have to create the trusted setup.
That Tau here for KZG.
And so where does it go?
Basically, the simulator here will create the
CRS or SRS, let's call it SRS, structured,
and we'll output that trapdoor.
I'm going to kind of abuse notation.
Usually you want to do something
like you want to choose that b first.
And if you're in the prover,
you have a normal SRS.
If you're in the simulator setting,
then the simulator can create the
SRS, which might be different.
So the distinguisher here might be able
to tell that the SRS looks different also.
So that's something that's possible.
So I'm abusing things, but just keep in mind
that the SRS might be different here. And --
Nico: Quick question!
What is this?
Is this our toxic waste?
David: Oh, yeah.
That's the toxic waste.
That's the trapdoor.
That's the secret point.
Nico: Okay. Cool.
David: So now the simulator has some extra
power, they can use the knowledge of the Tau.
Nico: Interesting. So it
would come in here as well?
David: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
David: So we would add Tau here.
And actually, if you look at the ZK
proof for PLONK and stuff like that,
they don't really care about
choosing the challenges,
because they have so much power already
that they can just use the trapdoor.
Nico: That makes sense. Okay.
And so here the order of things,
is it always the case that the adversary chooses
the instance and witness after the SRS exists?
David: Right.
Okay. So maybe we can mention that, but there
is an adaptive and non-adaptive version.
We have so many flavors of ZK --
Nico: Okay. Of course.
David: But here the simulator has
a chance to choose the SRS before,
or has a chance -- doesn't
have a chance, let's say,
before seeing the witness and instance.
So this is called the adaptive model
because the adversary can see the SRS.
Nico: And can adapt to that SRS.
David: And can adapt to that.
Nico: That kind of makes sense.
David: But if this came before, then we
would say it's the non-adaptive model
because the adversary is stuck
with a witness and an instance --
Nico: And cannot adapt to the SRS.
David: And then the simulator can see that --
So the simulator would see --
oh, sorry, not the witness.
Nico: Right.
David: The simulator would see the
instance in that non-adaptive model.
Nico: Correct. Yeah. Cool.
David: But it doesn't matter too much.
What we want to keep in mind is that
we want to give the least amount of --
or the more power the distinguisher
has, the better, generally.
Nico: So as a sort of recap of the properties,
we said it's okay to have
computational zero knowledge
because our adversaries are going to be bounded.
Adaptive, we want for sure because
our trusted setup already exists.
David: Or it's more like you want to
give that kind of power to your --
it's a better proof if the
adversary has more power.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: But I'm not saying -- and
also for computational, it's okay,
but usually perfect is better.
Nico: Right. Of course.
David: Or statistical is
better. Like these two are --
Nico: What I was trying to get to is
what do our protocols have in practice?
So if I do hide my PLONK commitments and I
do have these maskings for my evaluations,
what flavor of zero knowledge do we get?
David: So usually what you get is statistical ZK.
Nico: Cool.
And to my understanding, it's mostly about --
it's not perfect because you have some
points that won't work in a transcript.
Like for example, if the evaluation
points are in your domain,
domain of the thing, things don't really work.
Like there's some edge cases where
things don't work, but it's negligible.
And that's why we're in statistical.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: But it turns out that there
was a recent result on PLONK and ZK,
zero knowledge-ness of PLONK and that
it was actually not statistical ZK.
Maybe it was computational ZK, we don't know
Nico: Okay.
David: But it was proven not to be statistical ZK.
It was a small fix.
I think it was found maybe years ago,
but it was only published recently and
it was fixed in the original paper.
Nico: So it is fixed. So the original paper --
Well, the fixed version of the paper is now
back to being statistical zero knowledge.
David: Yeah.
So now we have statistical ZK PLONK.
Maybe worth mentioning also, about PLONK
like basically all the papers come out.
Actually PLONK was doing better
because they explain how to do ZK.
A lot of paper don't even
explain to you how to do ZK.
They just exercise left for the reader.
Nico: Okay. Write your simulator yourself.
David: Yeah.
To do that proof yourself.
But not even simulator, right?
It's like how do I even add ZK in my scheme.
Nico: Right.
David: At least PLONK told you how to
add ZK. They just didn't have a proof.
And so that was the prime. There was no
proof, or at least it was not statistical ZK.
Nico: That makes sense.
David: And I can talk a bit about that as a --
It's kind of hard to --
Okay. Let me make some space.
It's kind of hard to explain on a whiteboard
here, especially as PLONK is complicated.
But maybe I can talk about some of
the intuition behind the attack.
Nico: Yeah. That sounds perfect.
David: The intuition is, of course, that --
So we don't want to write a simulator.
If we could write a simulator, then
we would have a proof that it's ZK.
So what we want is to write an adversary,
but I'm going to write a different
kind of adversary because --
So what they did was not to
prove that it was not ZK.
What they did was to prove that it
was not "witness indistinguishable".
And that's a different
property, a weaker property.
And so if you don't have that, you don't have ZK.
If you have ZK, you have that. If you
don't have that, you don't have ZK.
Nico: Makes sense.
David: Informally, witness
indistinguishability is -- you have two witnesses.
So the adversary or the
verifier creates two witnesses,
and then they give that to the
prover. So you're the prover.
Nico: Sure.
David: And then you choose at
random or like however you want,
at random, most likely which
witness you want to prove.
You give it back to me.
If I can guess which witness of the two witness
I gave you, you proved, then you don't have this.
So they demonstrate an attack for
a very simple circuit for that.
And basically the problem in PLONK is
that you have this quotient polynomial T,
which was masked, actually was fine,
but they actually chunked it in T₁.
Nico: T low, T mid and T high, right?
David: Yeah, exactly.
I'll write it like that. So T(x) was
actually chunked because it was too big.
So you had
T low + Xⁿ . T mid + X²ⁿ . T high, was it?
Nico: Yeah. I think so.
David: And because they split it like this,
and they forgot to mask these polynomials,
these three polynomials,
then you had some leakage.
Nico: Right. Because these get
committed individually, right?
David: Exactly.
Nico: And then we're back to
this problem here up there.
David: And then we're back to this problem.
And so if I remember correctly, if you
write the equations with their example of --
there's like one gate and identical permutations,
it was a very simple example,
but they say it generalizes.
And basically you could see a
relation between T low and T mid.
There was some sort of relation when
you would analyze the transcripts.
If you could see that relation based on
the first witness or the second witness,
you could distinguish them.
And so the easy fix was just to mask them as we --
Nico: As we did.
David: As we saw --
Nico: Right down there.
David: Previously.
Nico: Cool.
David: Yeah.
Nico: Very good.
David: Cool. Yeah.
Nico: Does that wrap it up?
David: Yeah.
I think if you have any other
questions, I'm happy to answer.
Nico: Maybe a quick summary of everything we saw.
David: Yeah.
So ZK is important or not,
depending on the scheme.
Sometimes you only care about succinctness.
There's different flavors of ZK.
We like the perfect flavor, but we have
perfect, statistical and computational.
And these are fine, depending on context.
And as we saw, statistical is usually
what we get with PLONK and other schemes.
We talked about dishonest
verifier, honest verifier
and that dishonest verifier,
it's fine if we don't get it
because usually we are in the non-interactive
setting with the Fiat–Shamir transformation.
And we also talked about
adaptive and non-adaptive models
and we prefer for in the adaptive
model and these kind of things.
And I guess we talked about these two things
here, the simulator and how to hide things.
So simulator is the way we create proofs
and the simulator has different
powers depending on all these models.
Maybe they can query the verifier
and they don't really need to because they
know what the verifier is going to do,
or they need to and they need to guess in
the honest or dishonest verifier settings.
And we also saw hiding commitments.
So in KZG or Pedersen or hashes, how
can we really make it look random
or distributed randomly even in
spite of evaluations as well?
So how do we make it so that these evaluations
look random and don't leak anything?
And I guess finally we saw how PLONK
was not statistically zero knowledge --
Nico: And that was fixed.
David: Yeah.
Because they forgot to mask these polynomials.
Nico: One thing I really want to add
is this point to me is very important
and I've seen this mistake made many times where
people think hashing something makes it private.
And that's not true because that
is now a deterministic commitment.
And so you get this sort
of fingerprint of the data.
So, I wish people pay attention
to this and remember that.
Great.
I think now people can say they are experts in
zero knowledge rather than just ZK the acronym.
Thanks for clearing that up.
David: Cool.
Thanks for having me.